# Kiwamu Okabe - Research and Development Engineer

Phone: +81-90-3524-7064 Email: kiwamu@debian.or.jp

Homepage: http://masterq.metasepi-design.com/

### Interests

I launched my career on developing embedded devices at Ricoh Company, Ltd, and also learned application design using functional language such like Haskell. I found Metasepi project<sup>1</sup> what is trying to apply strong type to embedded programming. For my first challenging, I developed an embedded Haskell compiler named Ajhc<sup>2</sup>, and published some research papers<sup>3</sup>.

Today, I choose ATS language<sup>4</sup> as embedded functional language, and found "Japan ATS User Group<sup>5</sup>" what holds Japanese translations about the language. And I'm implementing<sup>6</sup> these technology on tiny MCU such like ARM Cortex-M series and 8bit AVR for practical use.

Metasepi is very experimental and ambitious project, however I believe that it also introduces an by-product "the technology to design real software with predictable manpower and safety" regardless of embedded domain.

# Work Experience

March 2015 - Present: System Enginner at Centillion Japan Co., Ltd.

• Software engineering for cloud computing

August 2014 - Present: Part-time researcher at RIKEN Advanced Institute for Computational Science

• Research embedded functional programming

September 2014 - December 2014: Software engineer at Axsh co., LTD.

• Develop an OpenFlow application named "OpenVNet" <sup>7</sup>

July 2013 - Present: Self-employed Software Engineer at METASEPI DESIGN

- Research and develop Ajhc Haskell Compiler
- Support to develop any embedded software
- ATS language consulting
- Manage Metasepi Project and develop the core technology

<sup>1</sup>http://www.metasepi.org/

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>2</sup>http://ajhc.metasepi.org/

<sup>3</sup>http://www.metasepi.org/papers.html

<sup>4</sup>http://www.ats-lang.org/

 $<sup>^5</sup>$ http://jats-ug.metasepi.org/

<sup>6</sup>http://fpiot.metasepi.org/

<sup>7</sup>https://github.com/axsh/openvnet

### March 2012 - July 2013: MIRACLE LINUX CORPORATION

- Verify PowerPC Linux and debug/fix SMP Race Condition
- Debug and fix PowerPC crash command's virtual memory paging BUG
- Design new Windows installer using NSIS
- Introduce and maintain new git server for internal use
- Verify and tune performance of Digital Signage on new hardware

April 2001 - February 2012: Software Development Engineer at Ricoh Company, Ltd.

### April 2010: Port OS to new x86 hardware

I ported NetBSD-2.0 to new x86 hardware, and calculated boot time before porting OS.

### April 2008: Develop and technical support NetBSD OS

I became technical leader to maintain and support Ricoh's multifunction printer. Also I debuged and fix many kernel level BUGs. I designed power down process by software trigger.

### April 2006: Develop POSIX thread library

I replaced user level POSIX thread library with NetBSD-2.0 m:n thread. My efforts are following.

- Research the presence of thread-safe and cancel-safe in kernel, libc and libpthread.
- Write test code to get thread-safe and cancel-safe.
- Add API into the m:n thread library. Because printer application depend on the missing API.
- Debug and fix signal BUGs in the m:n thread library.

### June 2004: Tune multifunction printer boot time as 10 seconds

Before my tune, the printer boot time is 30 seconds. Ricoh's multifunction printer "imagio" <sup>8</sup> use the method and tool, ever now. Develop a tool analyze log dumped by bootloader, kernel, init process and application. Analyze IPC network, and advice how to get speed to application developer. Split application as groups for pre-boot and post-boot.

#### October 2003: Develop new BIOS for multifunction printer

Develop new custom BIOS together at the United States.

### November 2002: Design secure boot for multifunction printer on x86

I re-designed bootloader to support public key algorithm authentication, and designed the format include secure key in SD card

### July 2001: Develop BIOS and bootloader for multifunction printer on x86 architecture

My first work at Ricoh. Ricoh's multifunction printer "imagio" use my bootloader design, ever now. Also I designed hardware dependent data structure to configure bootloader and kernel, and Option BIOS to boot on SD card

<sup>8</sup>http://www.ricoh.co.jp/imagio/

<sup>9</sup>http://www.ricoh.co.jp/imagio/

### Education

• March 2001: Master of Engineering from Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering, Tokyo Metropolitan University.

The thesis: "Multimode Quartz Crystal Microbalance"  $^{10}$ 

### Publications and Reports

- Kiwamu Okabe and Hongwei Xi. "Arduino programing of ML-style in ATS" <sup>11</sup>. ML workshop, 2015.
- Kiwamu Okabe and Takayuki Muranushi. "Systems Demonstration: Writing NetBSD Sound Drivers in Haskell" <sup>12</sup>. Haskell Symposium, 2014.
- Kiwamu Okabe. "ATS 言語を使って不変条件を API に強制する". <sup>13</sup> 夏のプログラミング・シンポジウム 2014, 2014.
- Kiwamu Okabe, Hiroki MIZUNO and Hidekazu SEGAWA. "強い型による OS の開発手法の提案" <sup>14</sup>. 第 55 回プログラミング・シンポジウム, 2014.

### Activities

Open-source projects

### Metasepi Project 15

- Challenge to create an open-source Unix-like operating system designed with strong type such as ML or Haskell.
- Rewriting NetBSD kernel using Ajhc Haskell compiler. https://github.com/metasepi/netbsd-arafura-s1

### Ajhc Haskell compiler <sup>16</sup>

- Extend and add embedded features to Jhc Haskell Compiler http://repetae.net/computer/jhc/.
- Ajhc has thread-safe and reentrant runtime. Also has Erlang style GC. It means Ajhc's Haskell context has own GC heap. GC can run on tiny CPU such as Cortex-M3 with 32kB RAM.

#### Japan ATS User Group <sup>17</sup>

• An user group for ATS language http://www.ats-lang.org/ promotion of utilization. Translating ATS documents into Japanese.

### Debian Maintainer <sup>18</sup>

• Maintained uim package at Debian squeeze, and packages using Haskell at sid.

<sup>10</sup>http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110004076869
11http://www.metasepi.org/doc/metasepi-icfp2015-arduino-ats.pdf
12http://metasepi.org/doc/metasepi-icfp2014-demo.pdf
13http://www.metasepi.org/doc/20141101\_prosym\_summer2014.pdf
14http://metasepi.org/doc/20140110\_prosym55.pdf
15http://metasepi.org/
16http://ajhc.metasepi.org/
17http://jats-ug.metasepi.org/
18http://qa.debian.org/developer.php?login=kiwamu@debian.or.jp

### Carettah 19

• A presentation tool written with Haskell. My slides http://www.slideshare.net/master\_q/ are created by the tool.

## Computer Skills

- Languages: Haskell, C, ATS, Intel assembler, Ruby
- Platforms: Linux, NetBSD, Android NDK, MinGW

# Reference available upon request

- Kentaro Kuroiwa Research Chief Centillion Japan Co., Ltd.
- Yasuhiro Yamazaki CEO Axsh Co., Ltd.
- Takayuki Muranushi RIKEN Advanced Institute for Computational Science
- Takashi KODAMA CEO MIRACLE LINUX CORPORATION
- Shigeya SENDA Ricoh Company, Ltd.
- Hitoshi Sekimoto Professor Tokyo Metropolitan University, Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering

Last updated: December 15, 2015

 $<sup>^{19} {\</sup>tt http://carettah.masterq.net/}$